some days ago I made a video about
flutter and why you should learn it the
video blew up and we got many comments
mentioning react native and how it
compares to flutter so on to this video
I would like to put react native and
flutter side by side to see what their
weaknesses and strengths are as well as
when to use one versus the other one I
have used both react native and flutter
I have built and released apps using
both of them and I also recorded
hundreds of hours of free and paid
courses using them both that is to say
that I have gone past all these shiny
features and Promises all these
Frameworks make and I have actually hit
some roadblocks and found some rough
corners and edge cases that could be a
deal breaker for some startups one thing
I would like to ask us is to avoid going
into absolutes one project is in a
hundred percent better than the other
they're both great and it is never a
good idea to marry a framework and make
it part of your identity or to hate
something so much that you would never
use it also be careful in the comment
comment section with people that seem to
be too sure of themselves some people
might have great stories about using
flutter and I'm sure others won't look
at Airbnb for example they migrated to
react native and then after a while they
decided they should migrate away from
react native back to Pure native because
of some problems they encounter does
that mean that react native sucks and no
one should use it not really it just
means that it did not work for airbnb's
requirements there were some trade-offs
to be made and maybe they did not want
to make them and this is what this video
will be mostly about trade-offs there is
no absolute answer and it depends on you
and on what your project needs so let's
get started with strengths and
weaknesses a strength of react native is
the fact that it is just JavaScript and
react the rules of react are the same
CSS is mostly the same and JavaScript is
the same this means that learner react
native for a react developer is easy
onboarding a front-end developer into a
react native developer is also super
easy and it also means that the pool of
developers you can hire for a react
native project is definitely bigger in
the case of flutter Dart is a language
that even though is not hard to learn
and even though it looks a lot like Java
or C sharp it is nevertheless a language
that almost no one was using before
flutter which means that the talent pool
is smaller compared to the size of the
pool of react developers and it means
that onboarding a new developer to a
flutter project will not be as quickly
as with react native the thing is that
in my opinion taking the time to learn
Dart and flutter pays off big time I say
this because working with flutter feels
like working with a big fully featured
framework and working with react native
feels a bit more minimalistic it's like
building a website using next JS an
awesome framework that has many built-in
features like routing server-side
rendering image compression API routes
static optimization versus building a
project using react.js only and having
to implement all those features by
yourself the same feeling you would get
if you compare building a backend using
Django versus building a back end using
flask or fast API by default floater has
many built-in features like navigation
translations dark mode gaming animations
some kind of State Management plus a
huge collection of pre-made components
out of the box all that comes enabled
when you make a flutter app and if you
don't find what you need built into the
framework the official Slaughter team
actually maintains other packages of
other things you would need like routing
camera access file selection Maps web
use in-app purchases Etc react native
does not provide all those things I just
mentioned out of the box you have to
install the many third-party packages
and write your own code to get feature
parity with what a flutter app has
enabled last default when I started
using react native in 2016 the project
was more like flutter the framework
provided more components and apis out of
the box but because the team has to
prioritize and they cannot maintain all
these apis and components they decided
to cut back on the amount of components
and apis they were going to officially
maintain to focus on making the core of
react native better having said all that
there are companies in the react native
ecosystem like Expo that are pushing
incredibly high quality packages and
apis that react native does not provide
by default like calendar camera face
detection Maps notifications among many
many others so on this point I think
Slaughter might be stronger than react
native because it seems to be more
centralized and less dependent on third
parties compared to react native that
centralization is good in a way that the
floater documentation their YouTube
channels the video series that they make
the tutorials it all comes from the same
Source flutter feels like the Google
product that it is but also that
centralization is bad because what
happens to flutter if Google lays off
the flutter team will it survive who
knows another point that I feel is a
strength to flutter is a developer
experience the integration with the code
editor is great and the developer tools
are out of this work upgrading flutter
versions isn't that scary either
compared to react native and as I have
seen on the comments of the courses I
recorded people have less trouble
installing flutter and getting a project
running compared to the pains they
experience with react native and you
don't have to take my word for it you
can right now click the link below and
enroll in our free react and react
native courses and then enroll in our
free Dart and Florida courses and see
for yourself the Achilles heel of Flora
that I know will make it a no-go for
some themes is called push code push is
what allows react native developers to
update their applications without having
to go through the App Store approval
process again and again because a react
native application is basically an iOS
or Android app that just runs JavaScript
developers can just replace JavaScript
the app is running by making the app
download a Javascript file rather than
rebuilding and submitting the app again
which means they can fix box and Test
new features in a matter of minutes
versus days flutter does not have that
because flutter apps actually compile
the code they run to Native binaries so
to update a floater app you actually
need to replace the binary the user is
running by recompanying the app and
submitting it to the app store again
there are some ways of emulating code
Push by using Firebase remote
configuration but what you can update is
much more restrictive and it has to be
planned in advance something about
flutter that may or may not be a problem
to you is how multi-platform it wants to
be the goals of the floor team is to
allow people to make apps and even games
for all screens and devices which is
awesome but maybe because the scope of
that is just too big and the surface
area of the project is too broad they
might be over extending themselves and
they might not be able to maintain all
the packages and apis of all the
platform terms they want to support I
have experienced this before where some
official Slaughter packages are not as
good or as useful as they could be and I
think that if only the floor team had
time to fix some bugs and just make
things a bit better rather than trying
to be so multi-platform the apps that I
make with slaughter could be much better
which I guess is what the react native
team realized a long time ago and why
they are focusing on one thing and one
thing only which is making the core of
react native great and having less apis
and components to maintain that is not
to say that the quality of the flutter
packages is bad it's great and I
actually prefer using a package from the
flutter team rather than having to use a
third-party package from a random
developer the way react native forces me
to so now the question is when to use
flutter and when to use react native
before I tell you my opinion I honestly
think that you should try them both I
made both react native and flutter
courses they are for free you can take
them right now see and compare just
click the link below and I will see you
there but to answer the question I
honestly think it depends and it depends
on many factors for example if a startup
is using JavaScript on the back end and
on the front end and it already has a
bunch of react developers maybe
exploring react native as an option
would be good the same could be said for
flutter if you already have a backend
build with Java and the developers are
all comfortable with object oriented
programming flutter might be easier to
get started with at the end of the day
both of these Frameworks are
cross-platform Frameworks so you will
face some problems whether you go with
one or the other but and here is where
many of you might disagree with me if
you are a startup founder or a solo
entrepreneur or a team of developers
starting a new project and you want to
build your idea quickly and you need all
the help you can get then I would really
advise giving slaughter a try I say that
because objectively flutter has more
pre-built out of the box features which
will help you move fast and get your app
in front of the users quickly and you
can combine flutter with Firebase
another Google product to get even more
speed in your development process I
think floaterbase plus Firebase is a
combination that will make you a Savage
in the app developer I really do of
course before committing to a framework
lay down a list of all the features your
app should have and then see which
framework supports the most features
which one has the most packages and how
well maintained they are and most
important of all don't let a video a
blog post or a comment prevent you from
learning something new try the
Frameworks yourself and then make a
choice the free flutter for beginner
scores is 7 hours long and the react
native for beginners is 5 hours only you
can watch them on a weekend and see
which framework you like the most which
one had a better developer experience
which one was easier to install and so
on like I said the courses are free so
click the link below to sign up and I
will see you there that's it for this
video let me know in the comments if you
have tried flutter or react native what
are your thoughts thank you as always
for watching
see you on the next one bye